Liu Bolin: By making myself invisible,
ليو بولين: من خلال جعل نفسي لامرئيًا،
I try to question the inter-canceling relationship
حاولت تقصي العلاقة العكسية
between our civilization and its development.
بين حضارتنا وتطورها.
Interpreter: By making myself invisible, I try to explore and question
مترجم: من خلال جعل نفسي لامرئيا، وأنا أحاول الاستكشاف والتشكيك
the contradictory and often inter-canceling relationship
في علاقة متناقضة، وغالبا ما تكون عكسية
between our civilization and its development.
بين حضارتنا وتطورها.
LB: This is my first work, created in November 2005.
ليو بولين: هذا هو أول عمل لي، أنشئته في نوفمبر 2005.
And this is Beijing International Art Camp where I worked
وهذا هو مخيم بكين الدولي للفنون حيث كنت اعمل
before the government forcibly demolished it.I used this work to express my objection.
قبل أن تقوم الحكومة بهدمه بالقوة. أنا استخدم هذا العمل للتعبير عن رفضي.
I also want to use this work to let more people
أردت أيضا أن استخدم هذا العمل للسماح لمزيد من الناس
pay attention to the living condition of artists and the condition of their creative freedom.
للوعي بالظروف المعيشية للفنانين وأوضاع حريتهم الإبداعية.
In the meantime, from the beginning, this series has a
في غضون ذلك، من البداية، هذه السلسلة بها
protesting, reflective
احتجاج، انعكاس
and uncompromising spirit.
وروح لا هوادة فيها.
When applying makeup, I borrow a sniper's method
عند التجميل، استعنت بطريقة القناص
to better protect myself
لحماية نفسي بشكل أفضل
and to detect the enemy, as he did. (Laughter)
وللكشف عن العدو، كما كان يفعل هو. (ضحك)
After finishing this series of protests,
بعد انتهاء سلسلة الاحتجاجات،
I started questioning why my fate was like this,
بدأت أتساءل لماذا كان هذا مصيري،
and I realized that it's not just me --
و أدركت أنّ الأمر ليس متعلّقا بي وحدي
all Chinese are as confused as I am.
بل أنّ كلّ الصينيين كانوا مرتبكين مثلي.
As you can see, these works
كما ترون، هذه الأعمال
are about family planning, election in accordance with the law
مرتبطة بتنظيم الأسرة، الانتخابات القانونية،
and propaganda of the institution of the People's Congress.
و بروباغاندا مجلس النّواب.
This work is called Xia Gang ("leaving post").
عنوان هذا العمل يسمى "المغادرون"،
"Xia Gang" is a Chinese euphemism for "laid off".
وهي كلمة صينية مماثلة ل"ترك الوظائف".
It refers to those people who lost their jobs during China's transition from a planned economy to a market economy.
و تشير إلى الصينيين الذين فقدوا وظائفهم أثناء عملية الانتقال من اقتصاد مخطط إلى اقتصاد سوق.
From 1998 to 2000,
من سنة 1998 إلى 2000،
21.37 million people
21.37 مليون شخص
lost their jobs in China.
فقدوا وظائفهم بالصين.
The six people in the photo
6 أشخاص في هذه الصورة
are Xia Gang workers.
هم عاطلون عن العمل.
I made them invisible in the deserted shop wherethey had lived and worked all their lives.
لقد جعلتهم متخفّين في المحلّ المهجور الذي عاشوا أغلب حياتهم فيه و عملوا فيه.
On the wall behind them is the slogan of the Cultural Revolution:
الكتابة على الحائط وراءهم هي شعار الثورة الثقافية:
"The core force leading our cause forward is the Chinese Communist Party."
"االحزب الشيوعي الصيني هو القوة الداخلية التي تدفعنا نحو قضيّتنا".
For half a month
طيلة نصف شهر،
I looked for these 6 people to participate in my work.
قمت بالبحث عن هؤلاء الستة للمشاركة في عملي.
We can only see six men in this picture,but in fact, those who are hidden here
ونحن نرى 6 رجال فقط في هذه الصورة، ولكن في الواقع، كل المخفيين هنا
are all people who were laid off. They have just been made invisible.
هم الذين تمّ طردهم من أعمالهم. فقط تمّ جعلهم لامرئيين.
This piece is called The Studio.
وتسمى هذه القطعة "الاستوديو".
This spring,
هذا الربيع،
I happened to have an opportunity during my solo exhibition in Paris
أتيحت لي فرصة أن أعرض لوحاتي الخاصة في باريس،
to shoot a work in the news studio of France 3 --
للقيام بعمل فنّي في استوديو أخبار France 3
I picked the news photos of the day.
وقد اخترت الصور الأهم في أخبار ذلك اليوم.
One is about the war in the Middle East,
أحدها حول الحرب في الشرق الأوسط،
and another one is about a public demonstration in France.
الأخرى عن المظاهرات في فرنسا.
I found that any culture has its irreconcilable contradictions.
لقد اكتشفت أنّ أيّة ثقافة بها تناقضاتها الخاصة.
This is a joint effort between me and French artist JR.
هذه القطعة تمّت بالتعاون بيني و بين الفنان الفرنسيّ JR.
Interpreter: This is a joint effort between me and French artist JR.
المترجم: هذه القطعة تمّت بالتعاون بيني و بين الفنان الفرنسيّ JR.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
LB: I tried to disappear into JR's eye,
حاولت أن أختفي في عيون JR،
but the problem is JR only uses models with big eyes.
لكن المشكل هو أنّ JR يستعمل فقط نماذج ذات عيون كبيرة.
So I tried to make my eyes bigger with my fingers.
لذلك حاولت جعل عينيّ أكبر بأصابعي.
But still they are not big enough for JR, unfortunately.
ولكن، للأسف، عيني لا تزال صغيرة بالنّسبة لJR
Interpreter: So I tried to disappear into JR's eye,
المترجم: حاولت أن أختفي في عيون JR،
but the problem is JR uses only models with big eyes.
لكن المشكل هو أنّ JR يستعمل فقط نماذج ذات عيون كبيرة.
So I tried to make my eyes bigger with this gesture.
لذلك حاولت جعل عينيّ أكبر بهذه الحركة.
But it doesn't work, my eyes are still small.
ولكن، للأسف، عيني لا تزال صغيرة بالنّسبة لJR.
LB: This one is about 9/11 memories.
موضوع هذه هي ذكريات هجمات ال11 من سبتمبر.
This is an aircraft carrier moored alongside the Hudson River.
هذه حاملة طائرات راسية بجانب نهر هدسون.
Kenny Scharf's graffiti.
و الكتابة الجدرانيّة ل"كيني شارف".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is Venice, Italy.
هنا في البندقية بإيطاليا.
Because global temperatures rise,
بسبب ارتفاع درجات الحرارة في العالم،
the sea level rises, and it is said thatVenice will disappear in the coming decades.
سيتواصل ارتفاع مستوى البحر، و يقال بإنّ البندقيّة قد تختفي تماما في العقود المقبلة.
This is the ancient city of Pompeii.
هذه هي المدينة الأثرية الإيطالية بومبي.
LB: This is the Borghese Gallery
معرض بورغيزي
in Rome.
بروما.
When I work on a new piece, I pay more attention to the expression of ideas.
عندما أعمل على قطعة فنيّة جديدة، أركّز أكثر على التعبير عن الأفكار.
For instance, why would I make myself invisible?
على سبيل المثال، لماذا أريد أن أجعل نفسي لامرئيّا؟
What will making myself invisible here cause people to think?
كيف سيحفّز جعل نفسي لامرئيّا هنا النّاس لتفكّر؟
This one is called Instant Noodles.
عنوان هذا العمل يسمى "المعكرونة".
Interpreter: This one is called Instant Noodles. (Laughter)
المترجم: عنوان هذا العمل يسمى "المعكرونة". (ضحك)
LB: Since August 2012,
منذ حزيران/يونيو من عام 2012،
harmful phosphors have been found
تمّ العثور على فوسفورات ضارة
in the instant noodle package cups from every famous brand sold in China's supermarkets.
في علب معكرونة فوريّة من كلّ ماركة معكرونة مشهورة تباع في مغازات الصين.
These phosphors can even cause cancer.
يمكن لهذه فوسفورات أن تسبّب حتى السرطان.
To create this artwork,
للقيام بهذا،
I bought a lot of packaged instant noodle cups
اشتريت كميات كبيرة من كؤوب المعكرونة الفورية
and put them in my studio, making it look like a supermarket.
ووضعتها في الاستوديو الخاص بي، جاعلا إيّاها تشبه السوبر ماركت.
And my task is to stand there, trying to be still,
ومهمتي الوقوف هناك، دون حراك،
setting up the camera position and coordinating with my assistant
إعداد وضع كاميرا، و التنسيق مع مساعدي
and drawing the colors and shapes that are behind my body
و رسم الألوان و الأشكال الموجودة ورائي
on the front of my body. If the background is simple,
على واجهة جسدي. عندما تكون الخلفية بسيطة،
I usually have to stand for three to four hours.
عادة يتطلّب الأمر وقوفي مدة تتراوح بين 3 إلى 4 ساعات.
The background of this piece is more complex,
الخلفية هنا أكثر تعقيداً،
so I need three to four days in advance for preparation.
لذلك أحتاج من 3 إلى 4 أيام للاستعداد مسبقا.
This is the suit I wore when I did the supermarket shoot.
هذا هو الزي الذي كنت أرتديه عندما قمت بتلك اللوحة.
There is no Photoshop involved.
لم تتمّ الاستعانة بالفوتوشوب.
Interpreter: This is the suit I [was] wearing when I did the supermarket shoot.
المترجم: هذا هو الزي الذي كنت أرتديه عندما قمت بتلك اللوحة.
There is no Photoshop involved. (Laughter)
لم تتمّ الاستعانة بالفوتوشوب. (ضحك)
LB: These works are on China's cultural memories.
هذه أعمال في المعالم الثقافية الصينية.
And this one,
هذا هنا،
this is about food safety in China.
حول سلامة الأغذية في الصين.
Unsafe food can harm people's health,
الأغذية غير الآمنة يمكن أن تضر بالصحة،
and a deluge of magazines can confuse people's minds. (Laughter)
و العدد الكبير من المجلات يمكن أن يجعل الناس مرتبكين. (ضحك)
The next pieces of work show how I made myself invisible in magazines of different languages,
القطع الفنية اللاحقة تكشف عن كيفية جعل نفسي لامرئيّا في مجلات بمختلف اللغات،
in different countries and at different times.
في أوقات مختلفة و بلدان مختلفة.
I think that in art, an artist's attitude is the most important element.
أنا أعتقد أنّ في الفن، موقف الفنان هو العنصر الأهم.
If an artwork is to touch someone,
إن كنت تريد أن تحرّك مشاعر شخص ما بعمل فنيّ،
it must be the result of not only technique, but also the artist's thinking and struggle in life.
فعليه أن يكون أكثر من مجرد تقنية، بل أيضا أفكار الفنان و كفاحه في الحياة.
And the repeated struggles in life create artwork,
و الكفاح و النضال المستمرّين في الحياة تخلق الأعمال الفنية،
no matter in what form.
بغض النظر عن أنواعها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
That's all I want to say.
هذا كلّ ما لديّ لأقوله.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)